Father!
Shut up! Shut up!
Help!
Shut up!
No!
Help!
Thanks.
"In the middle
of the journey of our life…"
-Good morning, Father.
-Good morning. Come in!
The Americans have arrived.
Good morning, Don Lecco.
Take it.
Show it to them.
Thanks.
Hey, guys, come on!
Let's get him out of here!
Shall I soon be a lady of the court?
In all resplendence, dear Gemma.
Who is he?
He is the young master
of the highborn line of Alighieri.
By Christian name Durante.
Tata, why is my hair not like ruby spun?
Or my eyes green?
Or my skin fair as a noonday cloud?
My friend.
You have revealed yourself
to be no one's friend,
but your own.
For I've been damned
by the very lips my sonnets took to sigh.
There are six priors. I am but one.
Would you have me
stand in defiance of the others?
The people of Florence chose this, not I.
Is this the Florence
that longs for self-rule?
I fear she is still a child.
I fear a civil war will come.
My dear Dante,
a sighing messenger of the heart no more.
I was once a father
more dear to you than your own.
When those you suffer to serve
drive you out,
find a nameless man
who calls himself Isaiah.
That's my last gift to you.
The delegation has arrived, Your Holiness.
Ah, bird of Florence.
My legates return to me,
unheeded,
bearing intelligence
that thy "republic" wishes more autonomy
to conduct its own affairs.
And yet the absence of one master
has made masters of all.
What say you of this?
A tree is known by its fruit.
And our republic's boughs bend
with sweets your holiness craves.
Perhaps I should give my scepter
over to the race of poets.
Will your rhymes finish St. Peter's dome?
Or pay my soldiers in the Holy Land?
Perhaps when reclining
on the slopes of Parnassus,
thou mayest set
thy utopian fancies in verse.
As for Florence,
no gentle inducement
will make lion lay with lamb.
The city burns.
And I weary of its smoke.
Ash makes little smoke and poor fuel.
If this be so,
I absolve you from sight of such calamity.
How so, Your Holiness?
I grant a boon
in exchange for thy insolence.
As such native talent renders you
ill-suited for the bane of public service,
Florence deserves thee not.
Forget her.
For it is she that has betrayed you,
though I pass her sentence.
Forgive me, Your Holiness,
if I have spoken rashly.
Turn from her as Lot did,
and gaze not in remembrance,
lest your soul become
a pillar of salty tears
that hinder the sweetness of thy verse.
For death awaits thy homecoming.
I place the mark of Cain upon thee.
Depart from my sight.
You're ordered
to vacate the premises immediately.
By whose authority?
Mine.
The Pope.
You have 20 minutes to get
all you and your children can carry.
A carriage awaits you
to take you to the estate
of Cangrande della Scala of Verona.
Upon the ground thou starest.
Is it hell that welcomes thine eye?
Or wilt thou gaze heavenward?
Beware, lest thy wandering eye
fall upon your wife's despair.
Your friend Cavalcanti is dead.
Dead?
Was not the blood of friendship
of greater value
than the honeyed wine of verse?
My dear dead Cavalcanti, forgive me.
Had I not made such a fool of myself,
maybe you would still be alive.
I will find the man with no name
who calls himself Isaiah.
Sofia is their true mother.
Yet the children of my kind turn from her,
never to know her.
Pharaoh, yes,
as the book of Exodus tells us,
killed every firstborn among the Jews.
But the false god of this new world,
which is gross commerce…
shall claim them all…
every-born…
and no Moses,
set adrift in swaddling
amid the bulrushes,
shall escape…
lead, and rejoin them to God.
The Arab is the new Jew.
For a Christian to be
in communion with a Jew,
with the seeking of what the church
may see as magic most heretical,
unholy and black,
it could mean anathema and death.
First they will kill me, and then you.
By this oath,
we both might be saved from death,
so we might then live to die.
No word or gesture
had ever stricken me so deeply.
In this seeming dismissal,
I felt more shame than anger.
My soul roiled with fear and unsureness
and damnations of myself.
This lesson in the form
of a silent blow of nothingness.
"Thus begins a new life."
Thus begins a new life.
-Good morning.
-Good morning. Mr. Tosches?
We're ready.
1310 to1330.
-1310 to 1315.
-Mm.
1315.
Good work
and good luck with your research.
Thanks a lot.
Thank you.
DIRECTOR OF THE STATE ARCHIVES
DIES UNDER MYSTERIOUS CIRCUMSTANCES
You seem to come to me as one in mourning.
I threw my work away.
Did I ask you to do that?
And you were right too.
It was the vainglory of myself.
I thought it was about the woman I love.
But I barely knew her.
We must not mistake
the revelation that our being is bereft
for the delusion that we have lost
that of which we've always been bereft.
Such a revelation is a blessing.
It's not to be mourned.
Countless words of love have I writ
that flowed from my pen
like drool from the mouth of one asleep.
And yet, not one for her…
who had borne me daughter
and sons,
and hath borne
my fate of exile and hers as well.
What do I know of love?
My heart is but counterfeit.
I have put half of humankind in hell,
and, with like strokes of quill,
looked down upon them,
aloof and unreachable like God.
Oh, God is not aloof.
Everything that breathes is God.
God is man.
This is heresy.
Think not of it as trespass.
Think of it as entry.
Because yes, every man's true
and only savior dwells within himself.
Whether he discovers him and be saved
or discovers him not and be damned.
And God is?
Aura.
Anima.
Breath and soul.
It's a breeze.
Sophia.
Wisdom.
Under every name, wisdom is feminine.
She is a woman.
And she was betrayed by the very verses
with which you wrought her chains.
You dared to give form to the formless.
Chains to the breeze.
Well, this breath is the only gift
to see the one life we have.
And there's no promise of the next.
Life is but a breeze.
A child brought to the grave
after but a few summers,
may, having drawn but a single breath
under the sky of illimitableness,
be said to have lived
a longer and fuller life than he,
even if he be king,
who is reckoned to have a hundred years.
You know what our main folly is?
Tell me.
Tempus fugit.
"Time flies," is what they say.
But it is breath that is the winged thing.
It is breath that flies.
Time is the folly
of our own vain making and delusion.
This anxiety that has come
to rule the pulse and rob the breath.
End your search.
Come forth from the tomb
of your seeking into the light.
And be filled with the scent
of the every blade of grass of your soul
and the every moment of life.
Come forth and embrace Her.
The FBI has
confirmed that American Airlines Flight 11
from Boston and headed for Los Angeles,
crashed into the North Tower
of the World Trade Center
in the September 11th incident,
creating a gaping hole
between the 93rd and 99th floors…
…of the Twin Towers' North Tower…
…one of New York's symbols.
Images show flames and smoke.
Survivors were immediately evacuated
through the intervention…
…of police and ambulances
which evacuated the World Trade Center…
I woke to the sky of summoning.
It was then
that I was ready to lift my pen,
not as a sore-shouldered and
world-weary field man his scythe,
but as a reaper of marvels,
rising to behold before him
as far as he could.
The rarest of uterine vellum.
Even our Giotto has never worked
upon the page as such,
but his colors will take as glorious
to this as paint to liquescent plaster.
As vision to cloud.
Your poem shall lie in a casket
of carved chestnut tree, hinged with gold.
Only the fair, translucent skin
of Beatrice in her virginity
could have yielded more fitting vellum.
For whatever of need or desire
may come your way.
The world shall have your poem.
You've given everything and more.
I simply do not understand.
A single year to write the Purgatorio,
and it has been six years since.
Paradiso is still unfinished.
I simply do not understand.
Good morning.
"I recently read some letters of his,
which he seemed to have written
so carefully,
for they were in his own hand
and signed with his seal."
"But by Hercules,
no one in this world is so uncultivated
that it would not shame him
to have written so awkwardly."
Oh my God!
I can't believe it.
My God!
Oh my God!
My love.
Then what would you desire?
That I might see what you did see.
Then close thine eyes and see.
O, Light Eternal,
that alone abidest in Thyself,
alone knowest Thyself,
and, known to Thyself and knowing,
lovest and smilest on Thyself!
That circling which, thus begotten,
appeared in Thee as reflected light,
when my eyes dwelt on it for a time,
within it
and in its own colour,
painted with our likeness,
for which my sight was wholly given to it.
Here power failed the high fantasy,
but now my desire and will,
like a wheel that spins with even motion…
were revolved by the Love
that moves the sun and the other stars.
God has breathed into you and from you.
He's allowed you this gentle lifting…
of the veil of the inexpressible.
You have entered the sigh.
You have become the poem.
I shall return your gift with a gift.
I thank you.
This book from him
will serve as entrance to him.
And the gold is… for the journey ahead.
There are a few clues I could offer,
for I myself
have never pursued the journey.
Why haven't you?
I was not one of the very few.
Why should I labor thus?
Because he can see.
If I find him--
You will find him.
Is there any message I should convey?
No.
My name is Jacob.
Forgive me.
It's no use.
I fear I shall die
with no confessor.
I'm scared.
Find your solace in the sky.
God is outside and inside of you.
He is you.
Nothing good comes from fear.
Oh, brothers…
who, through the west,
through perils without number,
now have reached… to this!
The short remaining watch
that yet our senses have to wake
refuse not proof of the unpeopled world
that lies beyond the sun.
Consider from whence ye sprang.
Ye were not formed
to live the life of brutes,
but virtue to pursue a knowledge high.
Dear reader, ask yourself,
was I not discouraged
by those cursed words?
I thought I'd never
make it back to Earth again.
Three.
Thirty-three.
Zero!
My friend drank too much!
It happens every day!
Let's go!
Relax.
Delicately.
My love!
Yes.
Over there.
No fucking way!
I'll make you shit blood!
Fuck!
My love!
Please, Beatrice!
Beatrice, my beloved!
Dread limits imposed,
a winding wend enclosed,
a lengthening cord
whose taut thou mayest see,
upon a dying star's tug,
time's trammels cease to be.
In what school were these phrases learnt?
The same that sweetened
the tongues of Guido and Lapo.
Undo these cords,
though no mortal knife
can cut those that bind us fast!
I am Beatrice!
Yes.
I am Beatrice that let you go!
I come from the place
where I desire to return.
Love moved me and made me speak.
O, Light Eternal,
that alone abidest in Thyself,
alone knowest Thyself,
and, known to Thyself and knowing,
lovest and smilest on Thyself!
The Love… that moves
the sun and the other stars.
By cunning, thou knowest,
is a woodman far better than by might.
By cunning too
doth a helmsman on a wind-dark deep
guide aright a swift ship
that is buffeted by winds.
And by cunning
doth charioteer proves better.
Charioteer.
Cunning.